the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
uh we'll begin uh nora has not arrived
yet
at least i don't think she's here um but
i suggest
we start uh and then benita
and then ria can have a conversation and
hopefully noah nora
arrives so welcome to estoa
uh for those of you who've been here uh
first timers still has a place for us to
coherent dialogue about what matters
most at the nice edge
of what's happening now i'm peter
limberg the steward of the stoa
and today we have benito roy nora
baitsen
and uh rhea bach uh here for a three-way
emergent conversation um so just a quick
intro which i
scraped off of their bios if you if you
don't know
these three ladies benita is an
award-winning author
philosopher an insight guide nora
bateson is an award-winning filmmaker
writer and educator
and rhea is a transformational change
professional who discovered a modality
called collective presence and uh these
uh nora
benita and rhea are friends of the stoa
they've been here before
and how this session came about
is uh benitez like let's have a
three-day conversation
uh with with myself norah and ria and
there's not many rules at the stoa
but one of them is what benita wants
benita getz
uh and so i'm like let's do it and uh
and i think nora said like let's have no
theme no structure let's just go in for
a
conversation so we just like let's throw
it up there
and uh and here we are so how is going
to work
um i was going to take in bonita in
to set the frame and uh hopefully
nowhere arrives but if not we'll we'll
make do
as as um good metastoix and
uh and then they'll have a conversation
and then
if you have any questions throughout
just throw it in the chat box
and then at some point i imagine uh
there'll be a pivot to some collective
questioning so that being said i will
allow every uh everyone to unmute
themselves
but everyone keep themselves on mute
except we need to and rhea at this point
so i'll take you in now nida
okay um um so
we had a little brief um back and forth
to see how we might frame this you know
the title is
wisdom practices and there's collective
presence form data
in insight practice so what do these
three have in common
there's a sense in which i mean it's
very obvious to me
that what ria and nora bring
is um there are the few people that i
know
that truly understand holistic
complexity that
truly take non-linear systems
dynamics seriously in their work they do
not
compromise and i know from my
own work there
are times where you do a workshop and
there are people very complex thinkers
very sophisticated
intelligence that do a lot of their dual
diligence
and they they use the term complexity
systems or
systems complexity but there's a sense
in which you can tell
their mind mapping all these feed loops
that maybe feed forward and feedback
as if theoretically you could get in the
system
and see all the parts and how they're
related
and that's not what holistic systems are
you can't get in between action and
reaction you see
and so there's always a challenge
when you're working um in this field
to try to point out to people that
no that's not what you're talking about
like no that's just not it it's
um and it's frustrating because these
are people who really do their due
diligence
put a lot of work and effort into it and
yet there's a kind of a hard boundary
they're just not in this holistic
non-linear approach they're just not
and i know that rhea
has is uncompromised
because she point this out in our own
work together
and the first time i met nora i was
asking her about her father
and i was saying um
you know it's hard to read him because
he uses terms like cybernetics and i was
like well what is he really getting at
and she just laid out this view of
the nature of reality the nature of the
world
um that was truly in the in what i call
holistic complexity i just used that
term to separate it from
systemic complexity um and so
i'm kind of stalling because i nora is
going to be here very shortly
um but but this is the seed that we want
to try to how can we
how can we better language or point out
this
the difference um
and do we have stories or examples and
how how we
how we kind of deal with that in in this
field
so um yeah that's what we're hoping to
build that
wisdom skill of truly
inhabiting non-linear dynamics in a
holistic system
um yeah
so um
when norah comes in we can ask her the
same question so my question for you
is like how do you how do you point out
the difference like how do you
how do you
how do you help people move from maybe
uh where they're stuck to a view that's
truly
uh holistic or non-linear
just uh jump in nora has a just arrived
i believe
oh great yeah i made it yeah okay
okay
i hear you fine i just had one of those
zoom panic
nothing opens nothing works ah
so but but anyway here i am hi
what did i miss you didn't miss anything
i was stalling
okay and basically oh there you are and
basically talked about
how we were going to talk about
non-linear thinking
and how um i said that i could count on
my hands a number of people i think
really don't come really are don't
compromise non-linear thinking when they
address systems complexity
um and of course you you two are um
two people that that i know that to be
the case
and i was talking about in my own work
uh and i'm sure this is
or i'm guessing this is for you too
you'll be working with people
and they'll use the word complexity
systems or complex thinking but they're
not really doing that
they're actually can't you know have a
lot of like linear
if they could theoretically they think
they could mind map you know they're
always coming up with these mind maps
you know of all this conflicts and so
how do you
language or what how do you build that
skill that people can exit that
you know and i was saying like a lot of
times these people
they've done so much due diligence they
read they study our work
and yet they're still kind of like that
click hasn't happened where oh my god
now i get it so that was the uh the ramp
up and you know if you have stories or
any way we can illustrate this
oh so many stories
um and and i i guess for me part of that
has to do with um
with the tension of being caught in a
culture
where what is expected at a professional
level
and in circles of change making etc
not just change making organizational
development um
academic work around stomach thinking
is that there is some way
to to solve it um
and and there's something deeply
entrenched um i don't know you know we
can call it mechanistic we can call it
linear we can call it
uh whatever whatever that thing
is it's some kind of control
um assumption
uh you can use all the vocabulary in the
book
you can talk about emergence and you can
talk about
interdependency and interconnectedness
and interrelatedness and you can talk
about coupling and decoupling and
complexity and and the second you start
with the idea that you're going to have
a goal
more than likely or you have any kind of
measurements
in the process of getting to that goal
boom
you lost it and there's just not very
many circumstances
in which it's acceptable to approach
the difficult situations of our world
without measurements and goals
so i don't know where the issue is is it
is it in the actual perception of
complexity or is it in
the way that there is an expectation to
be in the world around it
seems like there's some paradoxical uh
reflective
issues happening at that level
yeah i want to pick up from there
um
i think the
the mold that we are in the thinking
mold
of western thinking
and that's what i learned from you
bonnie is that very very either or
and it's either a solution or it's
either not the solution it's good or
it's bad or it's
lighter it's darker
and
even it's that
to actually grasp
that you live in complexity
and that even if you try
all these maps or
the actual experience
of of
and in some way we know that life is not
linear
i mean we try to have
friends and relationships and then they
stop and
even against our will and our
expectation
but this it seems like we have to
bring ourselves out of the mold of that
dualistic thinking that is so ingrained
and to
adapt something else which is
very fluid and very
not clear uh for many people that's like
because i think we are educated like
okay one
one is two and if you do this then that
and
which is all that linear thinking um
and what i find
um
when i try to explain uh the difference
between
complicated and complex as dave snowden
brings it that
let people understand that in a complex
system
they actually have agency
i've worked quite a lot with people from
the european commission
and then they kind of understand
complexity
and then they fall back into what we are
in the hierarchy
and so nothing can happen so
and they don't get
that you never know
how the ripples are going to
to ripple out or whatever you do as an
individual
might influence something
um and
that to me is is like a
some some some some not some some
crucial thing there
yeah i think that's a really good
distinction so um
you know yeah you'll hear you'll hear
people get more sophisticated and
talking about systems thinking so they
don't want to say they're trying to
control the system
then they'll say like mitigate or we
want to be resilient or we want to be
adapt all these things are hedging
that you can hear that they hedge their
vet and
and so i was when i was listening to i
was thinking of like
okay we live in a complex volatile world
every single person who says that the
whole reason why they're saying it is
like so what do we do about it
to make it less complex and more
volatile like the the whole
meme is sits in that frame
right so like and
and and we so we need to investigate
the mental model behind
the discourse and what you said riya
it was i think is really um uh
really significant and that is um
to have no control to not to be able to
mitigate to not be able to manage
doesn't mean you don't have agency and
that
is a huge distinction because i know for
myself when i get to thinking well
do we just you know
the the problem see that for me the
problem with that the way i address it
is you in complex systems you you don't
want to de-animate
any of the players let's say
and so to think you don't have agency
de-animates you as a player and says the
system has all the agency
right but you don't want to de-animate
the system or parts of the system as if
i can operate on
it without some kind of mutuality
so i think that was a a big
a big distinction and i was going to ask
like is there a choice possible
in this in complex city and so
this notion well maybe not the agency is
or something
that's a really interesting distinction
i like to talk about that in terms of a
paradox
um because it i think you think it is a
paradox right you
you you are you and and you know bonita
is is particularly bonita ish
you know and and ria is particularly
rea-ish
um and and that particularity
is your complexity it's your your you
know your history
your everything is in there the way you
perceive a situation what you
might do in response to it has
everything to do with
your frame your your language your
whatever your dna
i mean everything is in there um
but when you actually look at where all
that comes from it comes
from the contexts around you and so in
fact
you know you quickly get into a paradox
of well
well is any of this stuff that's i think
is me
actually me or is it from the context
and um and i i
refer to this as the the paradox of
agency
um and what's really useful about this
paradox is as long as you can keep from
solving it you're in good shape
um and that is that it it keeps this
kind of
living taught attention
um and by taught i don't mean teaching i
mean taught as in tight as in as in um
pulled uh stretched stretched attention
to um
to kind of both as being
what's there yes i am
i am um i'm responding to the context
that i'm around
in that sense i don't have any agency
you know you can vote for biden or you
can vote for trump
choose um and and
is that agency or is that
a choice that's set up within the meta
context and and and patternings of
of an existing system so are do you have
free will or is it determined you know
this is old stuff
but basically the paradox is what's
interesting
and um that paradox for me
it is something that keeps um
it keeps the humility and it keeps the
questioning
and it keeps the dance and the toggle
going
um between those different processes so
that
um i mean i guess it's harare right
who's talking about free will and he
says if you think you have free will you
don't have any
um because the especially in an
algorithm uh tech space you're not
actually making any choices you're
choosing between what's been given to
you to choose from
but the second you realize you don't
have any free will you get a little bit
and and there it is again that paradox
so for me this
ties into um again
that that attention to
a way of being that is essentially
in constant communication
with um the relationships
and and where they go right so you're
what you do is not what you do it's what
you do
and how that goes to the next thing
and the next multiple things that how
each path
enters you into more paths or or enters
the situation into more paths how
relationships build relationships
yeah and i to pick up on that nora i
think that's
important that to actually
have that holistic complexity viewers
as bonnie names it that you start
understanding way more of the
relationships
that are constantly going
instead of how i used to look a long
time ago it's like okay
i'm here and you're over there and
that's it as if there was nothing in
between
but in and
if you really embody
understand embody complexity then you
understand that there is this
constant influence going
all over the place from you towards you
and and
it's that that
that thinking of we are in this
skin and that is me and then if i talk
to you maybe we have a relationship
but otherwise not and that's
yes something so fundamentally
wrong is not the right word but that
that doesn't
work to understand how complex life
actually happened
for me it reminded me of something
schopenhauer said he said
i can walk i can will what i want
but i can't will that i will
and so for me it's like
uh it's trying yes it's a paradox
i i see it as tumbling perspectives but
trying to get a
proper felt sense on what you're saying
nora
which is beautiful and that is um
if i look at it from a certain viewpoint
the context life is giving me
i don't have the choice but to act as if
i were free
and that was not up to me
and so it's like
um there's a larger intelligence
in that design and when then i ask
myself if i
free will yes or no i'm actually
creating
a context in which it can't be
um known right you just get into pickle
some kind of conceptual pickle
but you can have these experiences where
um you have this strong felt sense
that i don't have the choice
not to be an agent i don't have the
choice to be a choiceless
i don't have the choice to not have free
will
but there they are i can't i neither can
i get
out of acting as if
and so for me i always believed the
action the felt sense the embodied
experience more than the pickle my mind
can't solve
it's like okay well language is too
coarse a
instrument to solve this pickle but then
you can have these experiences
and i don't want to hedge like then i'm
an individual that's that's that's not
the point and
and i think that like so why does it
matter and i think that
um we would all probably agree that
um
relating to holistic complexity is more
is has something to do with the kind of
processing your body does or
your actions and your feelings and your
senses
and if you can learn there's a way
a sense in which you can learn
to trust those and it's not like then
you get out of this system
and you can pick a direction
but there's a way in which your
communion or communication with the
system
shows you
things that were hidden in plain sight
let's say
shows you like
wow i was running around in circles and
really there's a direct link
from here to there that i didn't see and
it was easy
shows you that you make a move
and you know like those ripples
have more effect on the context than
your little move and that
they will be disclosed to you eventually
and now you're starting to feel agency
in the system
and it's very powerful
okay i want to tell a story when i
i was training in systemic
constellations
some of you might know what it is
and i always stand confused
because my teacher used systemic
constellations and there was
systemic thinking and i sensed
because i'm a very kinesthetic person
there was a difference
and i asked him like why are they using
the same
word systemic because to me it's not the
same
and he said
i think what we mean as
is that you you
understand that you're part of the
system
you cannot study the system from outside
as if there's a system and i'm here
but i'm always implied whatever
i do and that was for me i mean it's now
i don't know how long time ago but
that was for me such a
yeah a deep understanding about that
i i i want to go
into that thing that that bonnie you
started exploring there
around the felt sense and the the stay
with it
um and
what's in there because i think you know
there's a lot of people who are so
they're they're looking for a
methodology for how to get there
um and it's a tricky space to actually
put words on uh because
um there's
all sorts of of
possibilities for responding in in any
kind of systemic
situation and not all of them
are going to resonate in
multiple contextual processes
simultaneously
and in particular i think one of the
things for me that there are a couple
things that come up here
um and one is
that it seems to require
um you know we like to talk about trust
but it seems to actually require
a kind of distrust a kind of abandonment
of what the given
set of explorations might be to solve
the problem
in thinking okay but i know none of
that's going to work
all of that is going to end up in some
sort of reductionist frame
and so there is a you know a part of me
and this
this is something that i think matures
over time
and at first it might sound negative it
might sound
um it might sound uh
critical but i actually i'm not coming
from there
in in my life my experience with with
with the most um
sort of singing tingling responses to
systemic issues those those responses
come after you give up on the existing
set of
pathways so that seems to be one piece
of that
um another thing is that it's never
where you think it's gonna be
so if you start off thinking you're
talking about education
or you start off thinking you're talking
about um
you know a medical issue where
that other thing is going to come from
is i almost a hundred percent of the
time
somewhere else it's going to come from
another context
and it's not going to look like any of
the things on your list
of what you're looking for and and so
there is um there's that piece of it
and there's another thing that has to do
with uh recognizing
those things when they turn up
um and that's for me that's that's a
lifetime's work
and it isn't it isn't something that you
do
as a profession it's something in the
way that you live
you don't get to decide when that
form of perception or that those habits
of thinking about things are turned on
or turned off
um it's not when you're on the job it's
not when you're teaching your systemic
solutions course it's it's it's all the
time
um and so i i guess that
those things are so interesting to me
and i certainly saw that
you know with my dad in his later years
i wasn't around for his younger years
but it was something remarkable
because those things would actually
be in the immediate perception for him
i have to wait a little while and know
that i'm gonna have to get out of the
habit of looking for this thing that i
think i'm looking for so that
my it's almost like your eyes have to
retrain
to get back you know when you get
especially when there's an urgent
situation
responding to that urgency becomes very
focused
and and there's a need to have that
focus move
so that these other things can can pop
into
into your peripheral vision
um but but where are they how
and what does that look like and so for
me i think that
that process is a deep one and it takes
a long time and it takes a lot of
courage
um because
usually there is um
an expectation that the solution is
going to be
definable in linear relationship to what
has been identified as a problem
and generally it just isn't it comes out
of the sidelines
out of some other context
yeah i i wanna i wanna expand on the
negativity
because you remain so graceful through
it
um and and kind of like bring this to
practical affairs and
and so like um i agree with you you have
to hit bottom
like you're just so tired of doing the
same
it's not only that it's in the wrong
direction it exacerbates
the problem you're trying to solve right
and you're so tired
of of that and so
the so what happens is like when you're
working in these spaces people that are
on the stowa
or sensemaking community it's very
frustrating because again you see the
same kind of
effort the same kind of there's a lot of
novelty
into the grammar or the or the modeling
and yet again and you just want to like
pull
me this is my my experience here i just
want to pull my hair out
and you don't want to get negative
because there's something in the human
condition that is flourishing and people
are trying
and then you have to turn that lens on
you and say
no it's okay this is this is
this is part of it too like like
uh
and so the question like one of the
things
that i the way i talk about it is you
you
oh well one of the things that i think
poisons the well
in these conversations when i start
pulling my hair out
is i have a very strong critique of the
darwinian attitude of complex adaptive
processes because everybody's adapting
to everyone else it's just a
it's just a global reaction cycle right
we're adapting the climate climate is
adapting to us
the markets it's everything it's like
you know nuclear weapons and defense
and finance and prices and vaccines and
immune system
were in a closed loop and so for me
in complex adaptive systems thinking you
say well what do we do now
what do we and and and i turn it into a
process
uh i could try to combine process
philosophy with
complex thought and say what is possible
from here
well this is a surprise what is possible
from here and so there's a sense of
constantly
being rebooted and i like to tell this
story i read it in carl white one of
carl white's
books and it it's about he tells a story
about
this indigenous uh hunter hunter
tribe in northern canada or no nor
norway i can't remember
greenland maybe and their
ritual for hunting elk has evolved
holistically
because it's just an old
evolutionary uh um
process nobody thought of it and what
they do
seems seems tr seems uh
like magical thinking to us they after
they finish
using and eating every part of the elk
they take the shoulder bone from the elk
and it has to be the left or right i
can't remember
it's the ritual and the elders
who are skilled they
put the shoulder bowl blade over the
fire and where the crack
comes is where they head out in the next
direction
and he says the reason why he says
they're not stupid
really they know the elk drink down at
the water hall
at four o'clock but if you get in that
kind of like
direct control mentality then the alt
elk gets smarter and the whole system
gets harder and harder to
commune so what they do is they
introduce randomness into the process
and on the way they discover more about
their landscape
and they and they improve context they
don't even know they're improving
and the elk don't just become afraid of
them and then
the dance and the mutuality
is served by inserting by this this
relationship they have with randomness
and um and surprise and so
um yeah so when i hear
um hear people speaking
in terms of complex complex adaptive
systems
i i think it's not radical enough it's
it's
in the darwinian attitude and it just
escalates
it escalates action and reaction cycles
to the point that that's what we have
everywhere now
um so
ah that was my negative rant
i'll put it out there i know though it's
so frustrating because you know
when you start bringing in
anything that is you know what we live
in a world of direct correctives
and if you operate in complex systems
with direct correctives you
are gonna make
consequences that and consequences of
consequences
that you might be sorry you made
um so so yeah detours
and and and relational contours
and dances and things that were that
bring the the the expression that i
like to use is that the shape of the
response needs to meet the shape of the
trouble
but what we do is we make the shape of
the response
match the shape of the trouble and if it
matches
that's a problem but if it meets it it's
going to meet other things too
um but go ahead ria and then maybe we
can give some examples of that later
yeah i interrupted you sorry no
no um
because i wasn't i don't think i was
going to say something
uh let me check um
i wanted actually to
pick something up from from the what was
mentioned before that um
i think you nora meant the fel sense and
then bonnie said something about
embodiment and sensing and
um
i would say in in that gap where we
actually can
act and of course we we live
in context that's for sure and that
drives our choices
yes um
but there is yeah why do we do what we
do
why why did i end up here
i mean if i look at my history nothing
was
expecting me to be here um i always said
um
i'm just a little flemish girl you know
like from a worker's family
and
but there seems to be of a sense that we
can
be in touch i call it just life
life energy uh and and having a sense
and sometimes a very clear sense of
that's what i need to do and that's
something i cannot
not do if i'm really um
if i take myself seriously and my senses
um and in that way
i i always um
have advice for people like make sure
you
you know your body you know what is
going on
you know that what are these subtle
clues that you can sense in yourself
but also like what you said nora
to actually notice when the
emergence happened or that that other
strange thing that actually helps
um you need to be
sense sensible sensitive
is a better word i guess to actually
notice like hey
he was something let's let's pick it up
and not
let it flood away with
in the normal thinking and oh that was
just a small detail and
we don't pay attention so there's a lot
of
i want to put a lot of attention
on get to know
your instrument your body as an
instrument
besides all the thinking of course not
throw that away
but to actually uh have that also
available
yeah and i know i think adam roberts
here on this call
and i think his work toward you know
trying to
trying to language like perception is a
skill he keeps going it's
kind of the this core theme of something
that
he's trying to work out him in in his
work i think it's a part of that
you know um this perception
is um
you know we think perceptions frozen in
time you know by the time you're five
years old or whatever the thing works
right
and then that then we go on to teach
something else but
the question is you know i'm writing a
philosophy of education book and
i argue that perception itself
everything that
the core self the core perceptual
sensory motor cell
needs to develop over time along with
than the other layers
and it's not just a step like
development okay
you can walk your mouth works right you
can see things
and then now we're going to pile things
on top of that
um and our dogs are going crazy
so i'll stop there
it's great when you're trying to talk
about language and your dogs just
kick in um
so yeah i i guess what i i want to
kind of bring in there is that it's
it's also back to that context thing
like how much of the way
that you or i or any one of
uh you know us or anyone sees the world
as
actually them seeing the world and how
much of that
perception is actually shared perception
and i think this is where maybe
sometimes when i want to pull my hair
out
um bonnie it's it's at this place
where um there's a shared perception
and i'm not i'm not i i you know for
whatever reason
i'm on the other side of a one-way valve
and i can't go back to perceiving it
that way
and i get i i feel um
i guess that recognition that
perception isn't something that's just
at the level of individual
and so when we talk about how it grows
over time
it's also about how it's growing
in between us over time
um you know words that come into the
language or
or concepts that come into culture
or or experiences that are shared
that shift the ability to perceive
um it's it's that you know you can
when you add a coronavirus to
the perception that suddenly there's
another
way of actually of of perceiving
complexity
right if you happen to be looking for it
not for everybody
but if you happen to be looking for it
and that sheds a very different light on
education it sheds a very different
light on economy
it sheds a very different light on on
um systemic racism for example
the way that it was possible to perceive
systemic racism
after the coronavirus was different
it's like the alchemy of perception
changed
and then it was it because a lot of
people were looking at the systemic
issues suddenly it was possible to see
you know something else happen so this
this thing it had always been there
so i think it
i guess one of the reasons i'm i'm
saying this is that i i want to be
really careful about getting somehow
into um a linear education process
for how to perceive in this way or that
there's
levels of ability to perceive in this
way and that they can be somehow
identified
um which which drives me crazy
because i you know
work with little kids who are doing
really fantastic trans contextual
perception um
and description and people from lots of
different cultures at
many different education levels and
levels of
experience of betrayal in the systems
and and levels of
living in levels of emergency that you
would might think would preclude the
possibility to have such
beautiful abstract thinking and to have
the luxury of
pontificating and exploring in this way
when you have to actually deal with it
in your face emergency and
yet in those moments there are
definitely
a lot of people who are right on it
um so i just wanted to say that because
it can
it can be perceived that there's some
sort of
leveling up and i don't i think that's
the wrong metaphor to bring in so i just
want to bring that
so that we have it in our yeah
uh
how are your dogs bonnie
they did settle down
i was wondering if we uh we wanted to go
to questions peter
sure uh sounds good
so if you have any questions um throw
them in
the chat uh kim
i see that you have a question
uh if you can unmute yourself and ask it
i also
i think uv and mike have been have a
google doc
that they've been populating also oh wow
yeah that's pretty cool you're way ahead
of the game
so they have a section maybe um how do
we engage in non-linear thinking
um maybe that's something we can rift on
while we have some questions
come in the chat box
i see adam has one
adam you're gonna mute yourself sure
um i actually started
writing this down while you were
talking the session was
really your mic is pretty muffled adam
yeah
um well you know i think i need to
make an adjustment here why don't we
move on to somebody else
all right jacob you have a question
hi there hi ladies
so don't take this personally because
it's just a general frustration i have
and i'm seeing it play out a bit here
and maybe you can clear it up and i'll
do this thing completely different i'm
open to that
but i hear this thing happening where
like i hear all these ideas that are
some of them are good some are bad right
some and those those
the bad ones are good and the good ones
are good the ones that i hate are the
ones that are
super contradictive so you have like
i've heard like at least 74 ideas that
contradict each other here
out of the same mouth and so and then
thanks for laughing because this isn't
good i hope you see it's
coming from a good place i just care
about this a lot
um is what i see happening is that
there'll be a contradictory idea and
then people claim paradox it's like
well oh there's paradoxes in the
universe and we forgive ourselves for
our contradictions
because actually paradoxes are really
really rare they're like rare birds that
are beautiful and that
like you can't claim them all the time
like a sparrow isn't a paradox
you know what i'm saying like they're
they're rare birds
and so what's mostly happening is
contradictions are being called
paradoxes because if
you call contradictions paradoxes then
you leave them alone
but you need to if you know something's
not a paradox but a contradiction you
have to you have to confront it and deal
with it
so do you have a mechanism in place when
you're speaking and listening to make a
distinction between paradox and
contradiction
because if we don't we shouldn't even
talk i mean i take that back
but we shouldn't be in authority because
we have to be able to do that so do you
have some sort of mechanism in place
that can do that
thanks thanks for listening yeah
so that's where um
you can bring that kind of rigor to this
work and so
um i agree with you that most paradoxes
are contradictions i use the word pickle
most contradictions that we're calling
paradoxes
you can see that the semantic you're
you're
basically using words from one mental
model
and making some kind of category error
in another mental model
and you haven't you haven't i call it
semantic mapping you haven't
cleared out the clutter so you're using
the word for example
uh we made one distinction between
agency and control
okay so what you need to do
in fact most if not all of them get
solved i don't actually believe that in
that in the end you hold paradox so if
you look at the work of ralph stacy
that's where he gets to
but there's a move in which you can see
the paradox arises in a context a mental
model that you've set up
that necessarily
moves you toward paradox if you reason
within it
and if you can see the limitations of
your mental model
then the paradox goes away or the
contradiction i'm
i'm talking about those things we call
paradoxes
that you are saying are contradictions
so
um so there is a metacognitive move that
will resolve
in my opinion all of them
but you have to see you've set up the
pickle in the first place by the way
you're semantically mapping within a
metal
mental model so for example i'll give
you just an easy one
when we're talking about complex systems
people might say something and you
realize
that what they're saying is because
they can only say that if they have a
mental model of a certain type of
causation
you can hardly say it you can hardly
say this happens because or whatever
without inserting this mental model of
causation
and because you're trying to talk about
holistic emergence
but you're somehow implied this meant
this this theory of change this theory
of causation you'll come up with a
paradox
and then you'll realize oh i can't look
at that
and hope and hold on to the semantic
structure of this theory of causation
without coming to a paradox
hence i need a brand new theory of
causation
so there are people working in this
field that say what's the causal theory
in this domain that doesn't lead to
paradox
so there's a lot of that kind of work so
you're very bright to bring this up
um and um
yeah so so that's kind of interesting
work
if you wanted to actually say we're
capable of
we're capable of grasping this moving
from the liminal
kind of relationship to this to
something more metacognitive
um that's an interesting
career uh that that you could use it's a
lot of work
um but um
yeah so i have a chapter coming out in
the meadow modern reader that talks
about the metaphysical primes of
modernity
that will never ever ever let you
understand what nora bateson is talking
about
you have to exit them but if we
showed up using language like we have to
show up we use the language
and so when we so we end up with these
contradictions
and so uh yeah
yeah so i i like i love that work but
it's really geeky
that's you know it's really highly
highly metacognitive
i and i love that can i just say one
thing i so that was a long answer
i wish i understood more of it i would
have to maybe listen again but
so i think the answer is just simply
this you just need a bird book
to identify the birds
i i don't get it is that like semantic
mapping
yeah it's map it's semantic mapping
indeed yeah
semantic mapping that's what i call it
you asked for a methodology yeah
semantic mapping that's rooted in
ancient history or something but we can
have this conversation another time
think thanks you guys yeah yeah
but i think what you're on to is
something really important
because um what could be a paradox in
one context
might not be a paradox in another
context so
that's another issue that that is part
of
this you know parsing this out that i
think
it's it's worth paying attention to
um and
you know for me there's another thing in
here too is it a contradiction is it a
paradox is it a double bind
is it a dilemma right there's all sorts
of
different creatures that come in this
pickle
bottle um and and how
each one of these you know
sort of relational patterns of
predicament
um have um
they have something that is like a
portal
into a whole nest of relational
information through multiple contexts
and in that sense you know it's
it's it's important to
you know be rigorous with the grammar
for sure
but i think that what is also
interesting is to play with
that that entry point into
moments where what i would you know this
is why i'm interested in warm data in a
nutshell
is that that which is a an
article an artifact of data in one
context
is changed when you put it in time and
when you put it in
in complex moving responding processes
so what the heck is information when
it's moving
um so so for me the these
these entry points
the the pickles the paradoxes the double
binds the dilemmas the contradictions
the inconsistencies um
you know they're they they move around
and in different contexts they
they show up as different characters um
so i i think that's important too but
in any case they are openings into
relational
information
yeah so what is a paradox in
newton newtonian physics you're you're
you're curious you're looking around and
then you find a paradox
and that paradox dissolves in the
einsteinian paradigm exactly
um but when you're before you get the
new paradigm
your language is going to be paradoxical
because you only have the language
of the old paradigm um
yeah so um and then
i don't have all the sophisticated words
but
how it has worked in me is like
i come from the late feminist background
and so my worldview was very feminist at
some point and then there was the
feminine and there was a masculine and
and over time i i always explained
as i can expand my box and
suddenly that whole dynamic tension
it's gone at least for me and so there
is that
the individual and the collective and
having this at certain points in my life
struggle with that
and then so
over time i can expand my understanding
and then
that paradox or whatever we call it
is not an issue anymore because i seem
to have a
a wider container to hold it all or
something
i think and that's how we move on in
in understanding and probably also in
language
i don't know
all right uh adam your mic is
fixed uh yeah i think so can you hear me
now
yep you're good okay um
yeah thank you for this um i'll just
jump right into the question
um we spend a lot of time
thinking about or you know kind of
rethinking
how we might salvage uh concepts of free
will
right like that's kind of where this
conversation started
um and i heard nora and bonita talk
about um
well maybe there's a more kind of a
limited account of
free will as a kind of agency that
operates within
sort of different kinds of determined
systems and then kind of understanding
the nature of those
determined systems is some way of
reclaiming agency right and
as long as we're emphasizing the free
will poll
the goal seems to be something like can
we line up
all of these internal and external
variables
as best we can somehow account for them
and then then counteract them right the
goal seems to be
we're looking for greater control
greater freedom people use the word
sovereignty
right there's this whole work of like
gaining sovereignty
um and it's kind of like like you were
saying like
you end up creating these like very
extensive maps about things that could
be
like controlling you so that you can
control them
but i'm wondering what happens if we
kind of like run the system in the
other direction and and actually think
think more clearly about like what's up
this is kind of an emergent thought i'm
having as as you were speaking
is is there a kind of a positive version
of determinism just like we can
probably identify that there's a
negative version of free will there are
freely willed acts that we frankly would
wish
people didn't engage in um and so
i carry around you know these kinds of
oddball concepts with me like grace
and coincidence and flow
and these are things that
phenomenologically have the character of
acting on me or kind of picking me
up and getting me to do things that seem
to be the right things to do
things that i'm not sort of consciously
willing and picking up on
but the agency feels like it's coming
from the outside so it has that kind of
character of like falling in the
determinism basket
but it doesn't feel like i'm being
closed off
it doesn't have this kind of
mechanically deterministic
feeling to it it doesn't feel negative
and in a lot of cases it actually feels
like
by following that larger system or
following that nudge
i'm actually being put to better use
than whatever i as an individual would
have
you know put myself to do in my own acts
of
making choices so um
it's kind of like an intuitive nudge or
inclination
or um something like something acting
within you that's
that's not you and so has that character
of you being determined
but it also has this like kind of claw
like positive quality to it
and so i'm just wondering um what do we
think about that
are we still in the language of free
will and determinism here
uh does it make sense to to talk about
this kind of
grace acting inside of you as an aspect
of determinism that's positive or uh is
this something else should we use a
different language than determinism here
um and so that just kind of was shooting
up as you were speaking and so i just
wanted to know what what everybody
thought about that
interesting hello
i've i've come across that i
for myself um
some of of the listeners know the story
that at a certain point i was looking
for the book
that would ex describe what i was
experiencing
uh in groups of people and in dialogue
and
realized then that oh the book doesn't
exist
and it's probably me you have to who has
to write a book
and that felt like
something as i said i could not not do
that
and um
but deterministic is for me not the
right word
um and i have solved it
for lack of anything better in my book
like
there seems to be a level of of calling
you can call it souls calling or
um i guess that was the only word that
came
close to what i was sensing for myself
i don't know because
there's also something like there
is also to make a choice at that point
like even if i sense oh it's probably me
to write a book
i still have to decide myself there is a
choice to make to actually go there and
take the consequences
and take the time to invest in it and
all
all that i don't know if that's
any answer but i think it's
it becomes more
i see it as
becoming more important as we move on
short version
so
oh did my geeky thing
um yeah so the i think there's several
different moves that are in your
question as you composed it
adam and i think a couple of them i'm
sure you're aware of it's do i have free
will
well who is the i right is it
is it the persona
is it myself and then i wonder about
deterministic
or is it the universe or is it
let's say the universe is the whole does
the whole have free will well it doesn't
make sense
to ask if the whole has free will
because
inside the question it's a very
sophisticated question
very limiting limited limiting causal
framework
because when you ask that question
you're basically adopting the collision
theory of causality
my mind moves my hand my hand moves the
axe what moves my mind
you're stuck in a very in a linear
mental model of causality called the
collision
theory so
and that's what i was trying to say
earlier it's so the paradox of free will
is a byproduct of a certain
framework of causality
and so knowing that then when i ask
does the whole have free will i
i expose that because it's the if it's a
hole
then nothing's going to bump against it
to make it
move right so so that's one thing that's
interesting
and so the process move is is the whole
creative
right is there creative acts acts
denoble
novel acts in the universe and and
um then i can i can
i can work from that i can work from
that and
it brings us back to surprise and
unpredictable
since my actions are completely
unknowable and unpredictable and i'm
constantly surprised
the fact that i have no control means
actually i have free will if i
semantically map it back to the original
question
so we put these words in clusters under
different mental models and then we have
this pickle arise
um but if you make these move and
extract
like extract what
context what conceptual or
or perceptual context the question is is
lying on you
you can see that you've formed you've
created yourself a little pickle on your
and you're asking the question within it
um
so if you ask it from the hole does a
whole have creativity
and that's answering that if you
map it back down is the answer to
is there free will and but
but we're lacking a causal theory that
connects that
because we don't have a new causal
theory
i guess that in in addition to
what what ria and bonita have said here
i just want to add that i think the
reason we're asking that question
and that that question is so alive um
in western culture in particular
is because there is um
a whole sort of nest of
of um
boy complicated complex
both i would say
ways of thinking about this question of
the self
and what the self can do
and what the self has done and how the
self is
in some way identified with its doing
and it's what has
and and what has been done um and in
some ways this is tied to all sorts of
hero stuff it's tied to
um you know it it's tied to the way
we give out prizes and we say this
this belongs to that person or that
belongs to this person
so there's there's an awful lot in
that that
that sensibility that would inquire to
begin with
okay so there's two things that i think
we need to ask here one is
your question adam you know or or that
old
question right both of those things are
there what is the difference between
free will and determinism do we have
either one do they is it possible to
have a you know
a good determinism or but then the other
question i think is important is
what kind of what what does it tell us
about a way of perceiving
in which that question is being asked
and i think this brings us back to the
beginning of the conversation
um that gets to that frustration
around um getting caught in linear
solutioning
uh and and we're back where we started
from again and and how to
um you know this thing i say it all the
time
be in the system of the system and think
you can change the system
from from within it there's this matrix
sort of thing happening and not to
polarize with the system because that
makes it stronger
not to perpetuate it not to prove it
not to um
how how do you how do you where's the
change i think what we're asking is
where's the change and how can we
participate in something that allows us
to get to new patterns of living
perceiving relating
that are less destructive i'm i'm hoping
when i use the royal we there the
dangerous we
that that's why this this question is
coming up
it isn't always that but um
i think i'm gonna stop there but there's
something about
if you do something you can see that you
did it but
if you don't do something you also did
something
and
how to do something about the terrible
destructive
patterns of our socio-economic cultural
systems in a way
that isn't riddled with so much
of the blindness
of what it is that could be perceived
right now um you know in in
shakespearean plays
so often the characters perceive that
they're going to get ahead by
they're going to get to be king if they
can just kill the king
and the perception is if you kill the
king you can be the king
i'm i'm being facetious but but
essentially
there's a perception and and
getting back to sort of where where some
of the territory we've covered there's a
causality
that is perceived there's a perceived
functioning causality
and and if that
perceived functioning causality turns
out to be
let's just say limited if not
completely destructive and perpetuating
of existing systems
um you know i think the
the question that the three of us are i
think working with
is is how to perceive how to be in that
perception
of of seeing more of not all because
you'll never see all but not to get
caught
in the the goals at the wrong level um
yeah so i think that's part of this as
well
so we have about 10 minutes left
um might be a good time to
close out and uh so i want to invite
uh benita nora and ria for any closing
thoughts
maybe we can go around the circle
can you say something about what is
happening in the google doc and
something
just because i cannot do listening and
looking at
chat and google doc but
i noticed there was something happening
good to mention that yeah if i can take
mike and uv
for that yeah it kind of started off as
just a series of questions related to
linear thinking and non-linear thinking
and then uh also attempting to answer
them and then just kind of pulling apart
more complexity and more questions out
of it so it's
it's a little bit of a
confusing map but and then everyone
started con
uh contributing about i think it's about
double or triple the size than when it
started now
so i can see a lot of people still
contributing asking questions
hard to sum it up though it's kind of a
non-linear
picture of non-linear thinking yeah
thanks thanks
um i just i just want to just bump in
one other thing on
the free will because it illustrates
also the notion of paradox
because if you don't have the notion of
the collision
model of cause and effect you you need
to have a concept of free will
because if there's no cause and effect
what's what is free will
you can't will something to
and you no longer have the concept of
determinism
so this is an example of showing that
the paradox the pickle
is arises from a context a deeper
context
and that is there's an implicit
causality that asks the question
so i just i just thought it was an
interesting that it came up and that was
one of the big questions early on
um yeah
so what's the invitation again peter
for us here closing thoughts
before we make uh upcoming announcements
yeah i guess um we we had an intention
to give
people a flavor of there's a distinction
between a certain type of
approach that comes under systems
thinking
and something that we tried to
exemplify or share a language for you
um to um this would be my thing as a
strange attractor
because people are so many people right
almost there you know and
uh what kind of world would we perceive
if a mass critical mass of people
um lived in that paradigm
so hopefully we gave you a taste of that
or
provocative i think
the only thing i i would want to also
add to what
maria and bonita have said and thank you
it's been wonderful to be
in conversation with both of you and
really
delicious because it's um
i think it's time
to actually give
a kind of credibility and authorization
to um
to another kind of thinking and and
working with systems and i
i think we started off talking about
that frustration
and for me that frustration has
everything to do with
what happens when systems thinking
becomes
mechanistic and
that something vital something living is
lost
and and that lost thing
is going to prohibit its the the
the kind of
meta substantive aesthetic
um deep relational
and and second order relational change
uh that i think is only possible through
indirect response
and and having said that i i want to
give the caveat that
even um to this question of grammar and
semantics
even the notion of direct and indirect
could switch
so right now that thing we know as a
direct
corrective i i would hope
um and and i would suggest may someday
perc
be perceived as a really indirect
corrective
and those things that are coming in what
we now perceive as indirect ways
through multiple contextual processes
coming together and it comes from
the outside somewhere or so it seems
that that is a much more direct way to
actually uh be in this
dance or this interplay with complex
systems so
for me i think what i want to do since i
have these
um beautiful people here to say it with
me is i just want to i just want to give
credibility to that
because more often than not it doesn't
there isn't credibility there and
um without that credibility i don't know
how
we can begin to move into another
um another texture another depth another
rigor
of systems thinking
yeah nice to meet you nora
i've seen you once but that was a long
time ago and
i also want to name
the audience here uh
although i haven't followed
the chat because that's too confusing
for me but
um that's part of the complexity it was
not just
the three of us talking there was a lot
a lot more going on on all kinds of
levels
and it would
yeah i just talked yesterday with bonnie
like how can we
design this that even that complexity
and the intelligence that
because it's not just bonnie and nora
and i
who are the ones who know here
that's really
um and for me that's part
of actually embodying
complexity is like trusting the
collective wisdom
and looking for
ways that we can maybe need to invent
to to get more of that
or to i don't know that's
what i'm living with uh inspired by the
conversation yesterday with bonnie like
can we do whatever the ripple effect is
of this maybe
somehow we can
activate it more or something i don't
know
that's me um thank you for the
invitation
all right so we'll close here uh i'll
make a few announcements but first
bonita
uh nora ria thank you so much for that
beautiful and delicious conversation
um i would love to have you back for
another immersion conversation
uh if you'd like to continue this we
have a discord now um
here's an invitation for it and i think
i'll take benitez's advice and have
these like post-sense making sessions
that kind of daniel thorson does with
his podcast so we can kind of make sense
of this and embody it
and thanks for mike for uv uh for giving
that idea with the google doc live
that's pretty awesome i think i'll
incorporate that into
the stoa um so in the
upcoming events in 15 minutes here
we have a bio-emotive framework with
doug
pattern it's a really interesting
uh psychotherapeutic modality that
really gets to the heart and the mind
it's a 30-minute test or teaser
of it so doug's going to come in and do
a demo live so check that out that's the
direct zoom link
um we have a sense maker in residence
series
dave snowden who's mentioned here a few
times he's coming in
he's our sense maker in residence for
september it's naturalizing sense making
you can check that out the website
benita roy you have one you want to go
and plug that the holo
for october yeah so the holo is in the
legend of sleepy hollow a hollow is a
wooded riverine
secret place where people would come to
coast conspire
around change in the world and it's
apropos to the upcoming halloween
uh so um yeah so
um let's meet there in the hollow
and become secret agents of change
yeah i'm really excited about that one
that's in uh october uh fridays at uh
10 a.m eastern time or something like
that just check the website
um and we just post a new event that
brett weinstein is coming in
in september 21st at 6 pm eastern time
to talk about his unity
like uh 2020 project so uh if you have
any questions for him
uh just stress test it feel free to come
there uh and of course uh uh
ria bach has a a session every friday at
12 pm eastern time on collective
presence sing so if you want to actually
engage in these type of conversations uh
with us here at the stoa you can go rsp
on the website
uh and if you'd like to support the stoa
what we're doing here with all these
kind of free activities during this uh
meta crisis meeting crisis uh you can
support us on patreon
the link is in the chat alright so
everyone thank you so much for coming up
today
thank you so much peter nora and ria